In this video, I'm going to show you how
to use the new scatter on surfaces
modifier that was introduced in Blender
5.0 to add some lovely sprinkles to our
donut. But first, we need to model those
sprinkles because you can't scatter
nothing. Um, and I want to add my
sprinkle on top of my doughnut or close
to it just so that I can see relatively
the size of it is correct for the donut.
Um, and so how can you do that? How can
you add an object and place it somewhere
in the same motion? Um, and you can do
that by moving the 3D cursor, which is
this little guy down here. And sometimes
it's in a weird place and you're like,
why did it end up there and how can I
move it? So, you can move it by holding
down shift and then right mouse dragging
and then that'll place it on the surface
underneath uh your mouse. Um, so yeah,
it's placed it right there. Um, I might
actually move it up a little bit. Just
kind of Yeah, just about there. Yeah.
So, I want to see it just above my
donut. All right. So, now we need to add
a new object, and that is going to be a
cylinder, of course. So, add mesh and
then cylinder. You could also use a
sphere if you wanted to, if you want to
get like round sprinkles. I'm not a fan
of those. They're too crunchy and just
like I don't know. I always like the
long ones. So, we're going with the long
sprinkle with the cylinder. And just
like before, we're going to go in the
last use settings here. I'm going to
change my radius to the smallest cuz I
mean, hey, we're making a sprinkle. And
yeah, let's start. Let's start there.
Um, so probably should be a little bit
bigger than that. So, um, obviously if
you just like click and drag on this,
it's just way too sudden movement, but
holding shift might remember I mentioned
that. That'll use like smaller
increments. So, I think that's Yeah,
that's pretty good. And then I'll just
increase the depth of this to make it a
little bit longer. You know, something
like that. It's just a a starting block
before we actually start editing it. The
main one though is the vertices. So, I
want to add like a really um Oh. Oh. Oh
gosh, I hit the wrong button on my
Zoomit tool and I flew in there. But all
right, we can work with this. I want to
add a rounded corner to my uh sprinkle
there. So, we're going to be using a
subserve modifier. Um, and if we were to
add it on a mesh with 32 vertices, every
level of subdiv would like double that.
So, it' go 64 and then, yeah, 128,
right? So, um, way too much. So, I'm
going to drop this to six vertices. So,
super low poly, but, uh, it's what we're
going to use. All right. Now, add my
subsurf. Uh, I'm going to move me just
to the side here so I'm not blocking
everything. That's kind of the the
optimal place I've found for me is like
just right on that line. I only have to
move my head sometimes when I do that,
but otherwise I shouldn't be blocking
too much. Anyways, um now add modifier,
generate, and we're going subdivision
surface. And there we go. So, um the
reason we've got this uh diamond shape
is as I've mentioned before, it's using
the like middle points of each face
essentially. So, it has to go from here
to the middle point of this giant long
face. So, to here. So, it's now
averaging out those points. But if I
want to make a tighter, rounder bit
around here, I just have to basically
move out a point here to to add that
that roundness to it. So it only goes to
there. And then I would also do another
one here so that it's the the same thing
on the bottom. So in edit mode, tab, I'm
going to hit CtrlR uh to add my loop
cut. And then it's obviously saying
where do you want to place that loop
cut? So click there and then just slide
it up to the somewhere near the top like
that. Click. And then do the same for
the bottom. Control-r, click, slide to
the bottom. [snorts] Okay. And now let's
have a look at that. Just have a look in
relation to the size of the doughnut. Do
we want it any bigger? Do we want to
change the size? All right. Now, um,
yeah, I'm going to rightclick it and I'm
going to say shade smooth just so that I
can see how that looks. Okay. Now, we
could begin scattering at this point.
Um, but if we did, we would end up with
the same this exact same sprinkle all
over it. and that much repetition to
your eye just looks fake. Like every
single sprinkle actually the way they
make sprinkles is just like from a
piping bag, right? So you just literally
just pipe out a bunch of uh this, you
know, uh piping, right? Glaze. Um and
then it dries and then you just like
break it up. So they all end up in
different sized um shapes and stuff. So
we need to add more sprinkles uh just of
different shapes and sizes. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to first of all
uh rename this by hitting F2. I'm going
to call it oh boy late in the day
sprinkle. Okay. And now we haven't
really mentioned collections before, but
they're basically buckets and you can
move things in and out of buckets. So
there's a default one that comes in
here. Um, but you can move it out of
this whole collection by just taking the
sprinkle, clicking, and dragging it up.
So I'm going to drop it into my scene
collection there. And the reason I'm
doing that is now I'm going to select
this whole thing and I'm just going to
exclude. Okay. So now when you hit
exclude, it's not going to show up in
your viewport or your render. It's
effectively like it has vanished from
the scene, but you can easily bring it
back there. So it's just a way to like
quickly edit, you know, a bunch of
different things and then bring back the
rest of your scene. Okay, so here is my
sprinkle. I want to create variants of
it. So first I'm going to go into front
view mode and then focus. So one and
then numpad period. Now, what I want you
to do is to create some variance by
duplicating your sprinkle and creating
different twists and turns and shapes
and things. And I'm not going to walk
you through uh doing this. You should be
able to do it if you've been following
the series. But also, I want to tell you
something more important that every
Blender user needs to hear. Blender
needs your help. When you downloaded
Blender, you might remember that it
didn't ask for your credit card, which
is good. Means that everybody in the
world can have free access to 3D and try
it out. But what's bad is that Blender
doesn't have as much money as it needs
to develop the software. There are so
many areas of Blender that they want to
improve, they want to develop, but they
lack the funds, texture painting, the
whole physics engine, sculpting tools,
the compositor. So, the headquarters of
Blender, which is in Amsterdam in the
Netherlands, if you didn't know, uh they
hire some full-time developers to work
there in their offices and also some
full-time contractors from around the
world to contribute and work on these
features. Um, and they get the funding
from that from the dev fund, which is
the engine that enables Blender. So, if
you have been enjoying this donut series
and you've been enjoying Blender, please
donate. If you can go here and join a
monthly donation of 510 or if you're a
high roller 25 or higher is amazing.
This will enable more people who can't
afford this to uh to try out Blender to
to download it and so the software can
remain competitive cuz I don't know if
you know this but Autodesk made $315
million from 3ds Max and Maya last year.
Blender doesn't have that money. So, if
you want Blender and Open Source to win,
we do need people to donate. So, please
consider the link is underneath this
video. You can click that and um please
uh make a donation. All right, with that
spiel out of the way, we can get back to
it. So, I'm going to bring back my scene
now. All right, pull it out. And um
yeah, let's let's let's move this into a
new collection. So, we briefly talked
about collections, but they're
essentially buckets. They're just ways
to organize objects into different
buckets. And you can reference those
buckets in different parts of Blender.
But that's basically it. So, I want to
create a bucket, a collection for my
sprinkles. Now, you can create a new
collection by hitting that little button
at the top there, and you can just
create a bunch of different collections
and rename them. But if you want to move
something and create a collection at the
same time, you can do that as well. So,
if you select all your objects here or
you select them here in the outliner,
then you just hit M. M to move. You can
move it to an existing collection or you
can create a new collection and move it
there. So that's what we're going to do.
So I'm going to call this sprinkles.
Okay. And now that I've got that, I'm
actually going to uncheck it because we
don't actually need to see the sprinkles
um visibly in order to reference them in
our scatter system. So otherwise they
just kind of get in the way there. So
all right. So here it is. Exciting
moment. With your icing selected, we are
going to add in a modifier and it is the
brand new scatter on surface modifier
which is only there as of Blender 5.0.
If you don't see it, you're not using
5.0 or at least you're not using a
version later than 5.0 if you watch this
at a later time. So, scatter on surface.
All right. So, so many little settings
and things, but it's very wellm made.
It's uh I actually love it. It's a
fantastic modifier. I'm so happy that it
exists. Um, but anyways, the first thing
we need to reference is here. What
object are we scattering? That's the
instancing here. Okay. So, we're not uh
uh instancing one object. We're going to
do the entire collection. So, go
collection and then here click on
sprinkles. And look, we've got
not what we expected. What's going on?
>> [snorts]
>> Um, so the first thing we need to do is
uh first of all, why is there only one
of them? That's because density is
really low. If we increase density, we
get more of them. But still, it's it's
just getting worse. Andrew, what's going
on? Um, so first of all, uh, underneath
instancing, you need to check pick
instance. That's the first thing. And
that is so that it doesn't reference the
entire group as one thing to be uh,
scattered. you're instead referencing
the individual parts of that collection,
which is the individual sprinkles. And
then as well as that, it has reset the
transform because like it bases it off
of how far away is it from the center of
the thing. But if you go reset, then it
actually bases it on the point of those
sprinkles. Okay, cool. So, ooh, look,
we've got a alien looking landscape or
something, right? Um, but yeah, you can
see you can increase this. The higher
you go, the more sprinkles you will get.
Um, how do we change the rotation? So
underneath transform. Oh, right here.
Right where my head and everything is.
Transform. Okay. You get extra settings
here. So we want to change the alignment
axis. Um, and you can just cycle through
it until you get the correct one. But
yeah, it looks like Y is the one. And
then also, man, I should just Hang on a
sec. Let me just move me. Yeah, a little
bit. Yeah, there we go. Okay.
Randomize. So this is cool. Um so if we
add randomize here, check that box, then
go here. Now we can randomize and add
slight variances to um how it is being
rotated. So to rotate on the Y-axis, we
just increase that to 360. And look at
that. We've got sprinkles on the donut.
But we can go further. We can do so much
more. Um there's a setting at the top
here which is called surface offset cuz
you can see how it's like they're
submerged in the icing. Now, sprinkles
do submerge a little bit in wet icing,
but probably not as much as this. So, I
just want to increase this very, very
slightly. So, if I just hold down shift
and kind of drag out, I can get it to
there just resting on top like that. You
wouldn't believe, by the way, how much
effort it was to create this in Blender
previously. Like, bit of brief history
on scattering in Blender. The old old
way uh was to use the particle system in
Blender which was like old and legacy
and it was badly coded and it kind of
worked but it was you know it was
annoying. Um and then they came out with
geometry nodes which was all mathbased
and mathematical but to do stuff like
this required so much work to set it up
and then now they've come out with
scatter on surface which is still
geometry nodes. So, if you don't know
geometry nodes, there's a tab at the top
there. You can click it and this is what
it looks like. It's nodes, right? Um,
but the cool thing is is that this just
comes packaged with Blender now. And
this is already done. So, the guys at
the Blender Institute that uh, you know,
need your money, right, so that they can
keep working, they came up with this uh,
crazy math-based thing. So, it's got all
the options that we need that everyone
will ever need. and then only one person
needed to do it and then we can all
access it for free. So it means that
creatives don't have to dive into math
just to scatter some sprinkles on a
donut, which is what the last three
versions of this donut tutorial had to
do. And then everyone complained that it
was too technical. And it's like, yeah,
I know, but how else are you going to
get the sprinkles on the donut? Anyway,
all right. So the next thing you're
probably wondering looking at this is um
how do we scatter it in just a specific
area? Okay? Because you'll see, and in
fact, if you select your icing and then
uh forward slash, we've got sprinkles
everywhere, the underside, etc. So, we
only want them around the top of the
donut. So, how do we do that? Well,
there is a way to reference an attribute
inside of this. I'll show you soon. Um,
but the attribute we're going to use is
called weight painting. And you can
activate that by going uh at the top of
your screen there and changing from
object mode to weight paint mode. Um,
and I'm going to deactivate my sprinkles
so that I can just see the icing. Now,
if you were to click and drag across it
when it is active in this state, you'll
see that you get like a a heat map. And
as you can probably guess, where it is
red is going to be where your sprinkles
are. And where it is black, it's where
your sprinkles are not going to be. And
if you want to get technical, weight
paint mode is actually adding an
attribute to the mesh, which is where it
is red, that is a value of one. Where it
is black is a value of zero. And then
varying values between there.
essentially a heat map of values which
are stored in the mesh and then other
parts of Blender can reference this. So
it's a very quick way to just do some
painting on a mesh um to to reference in
different things. Now uh what is not
clear though is that when you're
painting in this mode if you go into the
uh isolated view by hitting forward
slash you might notice that you have
accidentally painted through your mesh.
I wish it wasn't like this, although I
understand why it is because people that
are rigging often want this turned on.
But your brush, you want to check front
faces only because if you don't do that,
then you'll still get your sprinkles
underneath your doughut. So, now that
I've got that, um, I'm going to Yeah, I
mean, you can like paint over the mesh
like this. A quicker way to do it would
be to, um, go into here where my head
is, data, then go into edit mode, right?
Like this, right? So edit mode,
everything is selected. If I drop my
weight to zero and then say assign then
go back into uh weight paint mode,
everything is black because this vertex
group thing here, this is the weight
paint, right? So you can select
everything if you want and just make it
entirely one or you can um make it
entirely zero. Anyways, now that I've
got that, as you can tell, I've got
front faces on. Now I can do my
painting. All right, so where do you
want your sprinkles to go? You just do
that painting, right? Um, and you can
have, you know, you can change the
weight of the brush as well. If you want
there to be like a lot that's kind of
just like on the edge, right? You could
do something like that. But generally,
you know, it doesn't have to be that,
you know, that perfect. You know, I'm
just doing this as an example of how you
could, you know, really do. You could
also go like weight one and then turn
the strength down. And then now as you
paint, you get like, you know, different
amounts of buildup. But, you know, how
detailed do you want?
Like, do you want I don't think
anybody's ever going to look at your
doughnut render and go like, "Wow, the
distribution of those sprinkles is
amazing. You did a great job
distributing the sprinkles." But they
might notice it if it if it looks fake.
You know, so it's it's one of those
things that seems like pointless in 3D.
Like you watch, you know, like Planet of
the Apes, like the making of that that
latest one. I don't know the name of the
the latest one, but I was at Sigraph and
I was watching a a talk where they had
the most amazing the guys at Wetter know
how to do a presentation, but it was
just like full of detail and like tiny
like cuz they had like monkeys in the
the the rapids and like just the
sheeting and the the the plants had to
have just the right amount of of wind or
else you and so like artists are just
slaving over every single detail. And
I'm sure a lot of them were like, "Come
on, who's going to notice?" You know,
and it's like, people will notice if it
looks fake. That's what they'll notice.
Um, but they won't know specifically
what you did, but they'll know if it
looks fake. Anyways, so we've done our
weight painting. I did a lot of detailed
weight painting there. But now, how do
we make our sprinkles just appear in
that place? Oh, yeah. Bring it back by
clicking that. Um, we do it here where
it says distribution mask. Okay. So
instead of this uh single value from 0
to one, we can change it to two. Click
this little spreadsheet looking icon. I
don't know why they went with that icon,
but anyways. Then from the drop-own, we
want to select group. Okay, which is the
name by the way inside of data. It's
right here. So if you wanted to change
that to be
sprinkle
distribution, you could um and then
just, you know, click it there. But
yeah, that's that's what it's
referencing. By the way, make sure
you're not using it cuz you can see
there's distribution mask and density.
They both have this icon. If you instead
used it here, you would see like almost
nothing. And that's because it's now
overridden what was there, a density
value of 900 with a value of 0 to one
across those areas. Whereas a
distribution mark will keep the density
of 900, but it'll multiply it by the
values of 0 to one here. So it's uh it's
important you get the right one.
Distribution mask, not density. But
there you go. Great. Cool. So they're in
the right places generally. You know,
you can play around with it obviously.
Um but now let's talk about some other
settings you might want. Like for
example, the density. How much how many
sprinkles do you want? Now, the big
question people have when they're
looking at this, they go, "How do you
stop the sprinkles from intersecting
each other?" And unfortunately, there's
not an easy answer because this is not
easy to do there. There's a such a thing
as like circle packing. That's the
closest thing, which is like you could
run an algorithm to try to combine
circles of different radiuses to kind of
fit together as best they could. But
just it's it's complex. That's kind of
like a simulation and we just we can't
do it easily here. The closest thing we
have is called distribution method plus
disk which when you click that and by
the way you can only see that option if
you're using density method not amount.
So amount will let you uh actually use a
specific amount of uh sprinkles but then
you don't get this uh extra option here
whereas density bases it on the scale of
the object in relation to the scene and
yada yada. But anyways, on disk gives
you this little setting, minimum
distance. And what it does is
essentially every single one of these
points here, it goes there's a point,
there's a point, there's a point,
there's a point. And then when you
increase this value by whatever amount,
it will add a circle around it, right?
And if you increase that circle and you
increase that circle, right? Eventually,
if this one, for example, had a value of
this size, this little dot here would be
removed because it is now colliding with
the value of this one. So, this one
would override that one. So, this one
gets xed. So, if we increase this, you
can see that is exactly what happens.
All right. So, I'm holding down shift as
I just play with that value there. But
you can see that's removed some of the
intersections, but there are still some
more. So, you might be tempted like,
"All right, let's increase that even
more. Let's increase it like cuz I want
to get I want to get rid of this one,
right? Let's increase it again, right?"
And you go, "Aha, I fixed it. No more
intersection." But now the problem is
the the radiuses are so big that they're
deleting each other and you now have
what looks like meticulously tweezed,
placed uh sprinkles placed along the
doughut um rather than randomness.
Right? So, we've gone from the chaos to
something that just doesn't look right
to the to the eye. So, really what I do
is I just drop this to be as low as I
can get it before it starts to feel like
too manicured. Right. That still to me
feels a little too manicured. I might go
like that. I might even go a little bit
lower. Yeah. See, that feels chaotic to
me. I like that.
And then what I do generally is um I
just change this seed amount here. The
seed amount not very well named but I
understand why they why they did it. But
it's it's just a randomness amount like
a distribution amount. Okay? You find it
in a lot of like procedural workflows
but it's like you can cycle through
here. There's an infinite number of uh
numbers here. And by the way it's not
like you know one is any better than a
th00and or 10,000. Like these are each
individual. It's just a random number
generator to uh give you different
variations. So, you could do that as
many times as you want to try to find
the best distribution that has the least
amount of intersections. That's probably
the best that you can do um with what
we've got. The other the other thing as
well is that sprinkles sometimes are not
laying flat right on a on a donut.
Sometimes they might be a little bit
skewed like that and that can kind of
help with the intersections. So here
where I've got randomize, I'm going to
increase which one? The X, right? Not
too much or else it'll just look weird,
but a little bit makes sense for what
we've got. The other thing that we
should do as well is with our sprinkles,
if we just bring them back by clicking
on that little check box at the top
there, um the point at which they are
spawned onto the icing is where the
origin point is of the uh of the mesh
there. And we haven't talked about that
either, but that's kind of you could
think of it as like the center of mass
for the object. It's we're not using
physics, but like that's kind of how you
think of it. It's like generally
speaking it should be in the center of
an object. You can see here with it
being there. If it was spawned like here
for example, the whole sprinkle is going
to be over here. Right? So if you've got
those circles of radiuses, it might be
intersecting something when it
shouldn't. Um whereas if you select all
of them like this, then you rightclick
and then you say set origin origin to
geometry, they will now be at the exact
center of that sprinkle and it'll just
be a little bit better and there'll be
slightly less um intersections. Um but
that's that's the best we can do. The
alternative way to like have sprinkles
on a donut where they're not
intersecting like this would be to use a
physics engine. Um there's a rigid body
physics engine in Blender.
Unfortunately, it's not very good. It's
very slow. It's one area that they're
looking to overhaul with more funding.
Yes, I found another way to throw it in
there. Um, if more people donate, we can
have good physics in Blender. That's
what I want to tell you. Um, but for
now, this is uh this is the best we got.
Or the other way is you could actually
apply this. You could say, "Apply all my
sprinkles." Um, you would have to
realize first, realize the instances, so
they're actual objects, then apply them.
Um, but you could then actually
physically move each of these little
ones like that. But I wouldn't recommend
doing that. I think it is overkill. It's
not and um it's not needed and it's not
going to help you for the next step
because we got to have random colors. So
yes, colors. Let's make our sprinkles
look not like tic tacs. So yeah, if we
go uh enable our sprinkles, right? You
know, we can come in here. We can give
it a material and you know we could we
could pick a random color you know get a
purple one and then go yeah now I want
to make a yellow one or whatever right
the problem with this method is although
this works and it is fast is um that
you'll always have the green one will
always be that bent one that little
squiggly one right and your eye can kind
of pick up on things like that um it's
also like hard to control the colors
right? Because I can't control how many
blue ones or purple ones or whatnot I
get across my donut. So, it's also not
ideal. So, there is a much better way
which involves, as I briefly mentioned
before, random colors. So, you start
with your material like this. And we're
actually going to give the exact same
material to all of our sprinkles. So, um
let me just disable those and I'll
select all of my sprinkles here. Um, and
if I want to give them all this same
material, all I would do is the last
sprinkle, as long as that's got a
material, I can hit Ctrl L. Ctrl L. And
that will transfer data from one object
to many objects. And then you're just
looking for materials like that. And now
you can see the uh where it says
material, there's a little number next
to it. And that actually tells you the
number of users that are sharing that
data. So there's six sprinkles now all
sharing it. And you know to be good good
little artists um we should call it uh
sprinkle or sprinkles I don't know.
Anyway um cool. So now if we go to the
uh shader tab I'm going to show you how
we can we can make this look cool. So
let's go back to the shader view. Okay
great. So there is no limit really to
what you can do with nodes. Um you can
plug things in and do this and that and
it's it's really cool. There's a bunch
of nodes. If you hit shift A and just go
in here, there's like all sorts of
attributes you can call in and do
complex things and you can get really
technical. So, it's it's a lot of fun.
Um, but the one that we're going to use
is underneath object info. If you bring
in this node, um, you'll see that
there's there's a bunch. There's like
location, you know, you could drag that
into the, uh, color, you know, there's
there's all sorts of things that you can
do with this. The one we're looking for
is random. Okay. So, what this is doing
is it's saying every time there's an
object that is using this material,
we're going to pick a random value for
that object between zero and one. Okay?
And you would actually see if you were
to duplicate this sprinkle again and
again and again and again and again,
which by the way, um, you can do by just
holding down shift R after you do a
duplicate, and you just get more and
more and more sprinkles. Um you can see
that they all now have a value between 0
and one and that's been converted into
color form because 0 is black and then
one is uh white. Right? So that's what
um that's what this is doing. So 0 to
one giving it that scale. Um have I run
out of undos? I've run out of undos.
Well I have to assume that was yeah that
was the last one. Okay, there we go. Um
so that's not very useful in this format
like zero to like like black to white.
It's it's not that fun. But we can
convert those single float numbers 0 to
1 into color format by between here and
here dropping in a color ramp node. So
if you go add or shift A and then go
color and then go color ramp, then if
you just drag this in and drop it until
that line lights up, drop it in there.
Now I can say instead of it being black
at this end, let's make this a blue
color. And instead of it being white,
let's make it a orangey color. Right?
And now I've got a range of those.
Right? And you could see as if I was to
duplicate, right? You get kind of like
variance [snorts] across this, right?
Every single one of those is getting
like a new little position somewhere in
this um little uh gradient over there.
Okay. And that's cool. And that would,
you know, if you looked at our donut
now, you would see that we're now
getting a nice range of different colors
across it. However, it's not quite
accurate. If you look at photographs of
donuts, there's there's not really like
the yellow sprinkles are all the exact
same shade of yellow. The blue sprinkles
are all the exact same shade of blue.
And it makes sense because they mix up
the the the sprinkle uh icing uh I was
going to say batter, just the icing
sauce. Icing icing. They just mix that
up with one like lot of food color. They
get just the color right and then it's
piped out and then that becomes the
sprinkle. So they all have one constant
color, not a range of colors like this.
So um by the way, here's a little a
little tip cuz you'll notice this that
like when you click on something else
like you're icing or you're hiding your
sprinkles like I can't get back that
material with all my sprinkles on it,
right? So I have to go here. I have to
enable it just so that I can click on it
just so that I can tweak the color. It's
annoying. You don't need to do that.
We've got a material here that says
sprinkles. So, we can hide it. And then
what I do is I just select my icing and
then I add a new material underneath it.
And then I which you do by clicking the
little plus button there. So, click the
plus and then in the dropown you're
looking for
sprinkles. Okay. And this won't affect
your icing. Like you can stack multiple
materials on one object and then
although we're not going to do it in
this tutorial, you can assign certain
parts of that material to different
parts of your mesh. For example, you
could assign it like that. Um, but you
can also just leave it unassigned and
then that way you can like quickly
reference it. So that's what I like to
do. So I've still got my glaze at the
top there and then whenever I want to
change my sprinkles, they're there and
it's being shared across all the
sprinkles that are hidden. Anyways, so
as I mentioned, I want it to be a
constant color. How can I make this look
like a constant color? You can do it by
changing these handles from instead of
it being linear interpolation to a
constant interpolation. And look at
that. Now it is a hard line. It's not a
a gradient across it. You only get all
of this blue or all of this uh orange.
So, you know, if you wanted to make a uh
Halloween donut,
right, you can go for something.
I I moved to United States a couple of
years ago. coming up on two years ago.
And uh I'm just learning that that's the
colors of Halloween because we don't
really do Halloween in Australia where
I'm from. Like some people do, but it's
really a kind of a rare thing that
people are into. But it's always Yeah,
it's the black, orange, the green, and
the purple seems to be the uh the colors
that people like decorate their houses
with and stuff. And Reese's pieces
really lean into that. They love that
they're one of those colors.
You know, you can do you can do like fun
stuff, right? You can make up the
Halloween looking uh donut if you wanted
to. Um what I'm going to do for mine is
um I'm going to make mine look like
pastel. Um so I like to go with like a
shade of aqua kind of like that. And
then I'm going to go with purple like
that. And this is a a tip by the way.
You never want to go like 100%
um like saturated like that. Um that's
weird. Why is no donut got that exact?
Well, they are. They're just being
washed out. Okay, they don't look very
very extremely saturated. But anyways,
um you never want to go like fully
saturated like that because it can like
using different uh the way you render
it. If you put it like through a like a
a contrast, you kind of like boost
highlights or like make things more
contrasted, it can kind of like blow out
the colors. So, it's it's generally a
good idea to leave things mostly
unsaturated like this. It's also just
like more pleasing on the eye if you
don't have too many things that are
like, you know, extremely intense. Um,
and now this is the other thing as I
mentioned, right? I can now choose the
exact ratio of my sprinkles. More blue,
more purple, more pink, more yellow. And
I just have an exact easy slider to
choose this. Um, and this is really fun.
This is like where you get to be
creative and go like what kind of what
kind of donut am I going to be making
here? You know, um like this, you know,
you can make some white ones.
But yeah, generally as a a rule of
advice um when you're when you're making
something um like this and you've got
lots of colors, lots of potential color
choices, it's best to try to go with
like one primary color, like one that is
making up the predominant color choice,
right? So you go like mostly purple and
then like a few splashes of other colors
and it just helps it. It's it's almost
like it helps your brain digest what
it's looking at. Whereas if you just
went like evenly distributed across all
of them or get an equal share, it just
starts to look a little bit like noise.
Um by the way, the other thing that you
might want to do at this point Oh, I'm
already using it. I'm using medium high
contrast. Um, but we're going to be So,
by default, your color management, it
kind of looks like this. So, your colors
look a little bit washed out. And we're
not going to get into color management,
but essentially like everything is kind
of a little bit desaturated. Um, and
it's designed so that it makes it easier
to grade, but it's not really designed
for a final render when you're using the
none look. Instead, you're better off
using uh medium high or high contrast or
for a YouTube thumbnail. Very high
contrast. That's what I use. Um, and
these aren't like bad. It's not like
they're doing like a rough like contrast
grab or something. This is like a proper
S- log um uh sorry S-curve uh
conversion. Um nothing is peing. It's
all It's all this I I use these all the
time. Medium high, medium uh yeah or or
high. Um anyways, so that's pretty good.
And then I might grab my Oh, yeah. I got
to fix this again. Let's make that back
what it was. Let's move that back.
Get a few more blues in there.
Bit of pinks, bit of whites, bit of
yellows. I'm going to make my icing as
well a little bit hotter. And I'm going
to tweak it a little more towards the
purple range. Just a little bit. Back at
the sprinkles. The other thing I forgot
to mention as well, um, sprinkles are
actually a little bit shiny if you look
at references. So, a little bit shiny.
And then the other thing it really
needs, and this does make a big
difference, is subsurface scattering.
So, just like before, dragging down on
that radius to make them all one. And
then I'm increasing the weight to be
one. And then I just dropped this scale
to be something really low. But that
will make a big difference. I was before
I was like practicing for this this uh
video. Um and I was like, why are my
sprinkles just not looking good? They
weren't looking as good as um you know,
a previous render I'd done and I forgot
subsurface scattering. And it does make
uh a huge difference. So there we go.
We've got a nice looking doughut. Before
you go ahead, what I'd like you to do is
to try to create your own
style of doughut. Um, you could try
substituting the long sprinkles for like
rounded sprinkles or like star- shaped
sprinkles. Um, you could change the
doughut color to be something else. You
could make more donuts by just stacking
donuts on top of each other. Um, here
are some ideas that uh my team and over
the years we different donut versions
and stuff we've we've created. Um, but
you can do a lot. So have fun just
experimenting and trying to create
something of your own with your own
creativity uh injected into it. And
it'll also just kind of teach you to
kind of think independently and like
where is this thing and locate that and
it's you know just a way of like
bringing back that information and also
as your homework uh add some sprinkles
to your plate if you want. Um I won't
show you how to do it because it's
basically the same steps as before
scattering on surface. The only thing uh
I'll mention is that you do need to
apply your solidify modifier so that you
can actually paint on the correct side
of your plate and they will appear um as
long as that's done. But it's super
simple. So I trust you all be able to do
that. Anyways, that's it for this video.
Join me in the next part, the final part
as we do the lighting and rendering.